<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SisterAnalyst</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>SisterAnalyst</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/SA_hex.png</url>
      <title>SisterAnalyst</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>/programmes/programmes/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/programmes/programmes/overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;fundamental-ds-and-ai-skills-data-skills-for-work&#34;&gt;Fundamental DS and AI skills: data skills for work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Science (DS) and Artificial Intelligence (AI) are an essential part of a data-driven culture. The aim of this course is to provide a solid foundation for understanding data, in particular how to read, work with, analyse and communicate with data. They are skills that empower people from all walks of life at all levels of work. It is a set of skills that is also likely to improve digital literacy. As data is so crucial for organisational success, data literacy and associated meta-skills are intrinsically in demand for all employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By applying AI algorithms, we draw answers from data, which is why fundamental coding and data skills are necessary for developing strong conceptual understanding of the technologies behind AI. Our course will develop your confidence and skills to drive and sustain data driven innovation whether you study, work or you acquire them for your everyday life. The course focuses on teaching individuals the practical and technical skills needed to analyse and solve intricate data problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the course, you will be introduced to a wide variety of free and open source tools commonly used when working on a data project. You will apply these tools in many practical activities and case studies, solving problems that involve finding and evaluating information, performing calculations and data wrangling that will enable you to draw reasoned conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will start from zero, with no prior knowledge required, and work our way up to advanced data analysis using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, a public domain language for data analysis. The curriculum covers the relevant tools and technologies including Fundamental Coding and Basic Statistical Concepts through the use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. R amalgamates the learning of important and desirable data skills: code writing for statistical modelling, and visualisation and data reporting in a reproducible manner. You will learn how to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;, a version control system, to track changes when working on a data project in a transparent and reproducible manner that fosters knowledge sharing and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be guided by skilled instructors and will gain real-world experience by collaborating with your peers on real-life data projects provided by our partner companies and organisations. You will build a comprehensive portfolio throughout the learning experience, giving you the confidence needed to tap into related industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our local and international partners will provide a unique opportunity for you to work on real-life projects that will help grow your skills, build your profile, and create a platform for your data literacy empowered career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the course you will have the solid understanding needed to be able to further grow your data knowledge skills once the course is complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;course-objectives&#34;&gt;Course Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn fundamental concepts of computer coding along with problem solving techniques and analytical thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to analyse problem requirements to recognise what type of data and processes are involved in the solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to navigate the entire data science pipeline from data acquisition to publication: access, explore, visualise, and analyse data in a reproducible and shareable manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on case studies inspired by real problems and based on real-world data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become aware of, and recognise the huge potential for data science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-course-works-teaching-and-learning-strategy&#34;&gt;How the course works: Teaching and Learning Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material is structured within a series of eight weekly specialised units that will help you master the skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each unit is split into two hands-on taught lessons that will be delivered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wednesdays, between 18:00 - 21:00 as an on-line session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturdays, between 10:00 - 14:00 as an on-site session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and it will require a minimum of 3 hours guided independent study time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each unit will be taught by our instructors and will cover various related topics through appropriate case studies, presentations, readings and discussion forums. The conceptual ideas come to life when practice becomes reality which is why the material is designed as hands-on taught lessons, through the application of R. The course provides the opportunity for participants to test their knowledge, both conceptual and practical by adopting an interactive student/teacher approach. Students are expected to use their own time to practise and hone the data handling expertise acquired during the sessions.
To provide a structure in learning to communicate newly acquired concepts you will be paired with a fellow student. You will practise explaining new concepts and skills to one another, which will advance your learning and develop the essential collaboration skills you will need in a data driven work place environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students are expected to participate fully in all of these delivery modes, but in particular are expected to have attempted any pre-set work, and come fully prepared to discuss any problems encountered and debate the ideas and any issues raised. We recommend you complete each of the following before the end of each week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readings and hand-outs/exercises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participation in the discussion forums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quizzes covering concepts from tutorials and/or readings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To earn your certificate, you will need to successfully complete the final project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Course material will be delivered in English and Serbian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-can-enrol&#34;&gt;Who can enrol&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is for people from varying backgrounds and diverse profiles with very little or no coding or data analytic experience. The course will benefit anyone who has the curiosity and desire to enter the realm of data science. We will make sense of the world of data and learn effective and attractive ways to visually analyse and communicate related information. With the knowledge gained on this course, you will be ready to undertake your very own data analysis for the first time.
Data Science is not simply fashionable jargon, but rather a set of tools that empower data enriched
living, so whatever industry you are in, this is relevant to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-is-eligible-for-our-course&#34;&gt;Who is eligible for our course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women and gender minorities over 18 years of age with priority given to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single Parents on low income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long-term unemployed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone experiencing problems getting the education needed to find meaningful work, through discrimination or otherwise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-can-apply-for-our-course&#34;&gt;Who can apply for our course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who recognise the paramount importance of data and its use and are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Able to commit to the course for its duration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Able to commit to all required sessions and the time requirements specified&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willing to share knowledge and return as a mentor or coach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The course is delivered twice a year.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our next available cohort starts on 02 March 2022.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indicative Syllabus</title>
      <link>/programmes/programmes/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/programmes/programmes/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Learning units build on previous units and they should be learnt in the order presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-1&#34;&gt;Unit 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core DS/AI Concepts and Tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unit will cover the baseline knowledge you need before getting into the advanced coding aspects of DS/AI. We will discuss concepts and terminology related to data and data solutions. You will learn the fundamentals of computer science with “drag &amp;amp; drop blocks”. In order to become acquainted with the basic computational concepts of problem-solving, logical thinking, cause and effect within the context of modelling, you will be introduced to prime programming operations, control structures, data types, etc. We will finish by configuring your working environment and installing the software necessary when working on your future data projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To describe forms, formats, and lifecycles of data and how these vary across disciplines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To represent programming logic in pseudocode and/or flowcharts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic concepts such as data type and index&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use Boolean expressions in if-then structures for making decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use looping structures and how to end loops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create your own customised functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To install and run R/RStudio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-2&#34;&gt;Unit 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R in RStudio: syntax and working environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this module you will set up the working environment and pass the first big hurdle of importing data; you will learn how to do it the proper way with a command in R. You will learn how to use RStudio IDE for R from RStudio customisation to files navigation. You will learn good habits and practice of workflow in an R project. Once you get comfortable with the RStudio working environment, you will move on to mastering the key features of R language and its syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic use of R/RStudio console&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good habits for workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data structures, variables, and basic data collection techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inputting and importing different data types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R environment: record keeping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-3&#34;&gt;Unit 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Git in GitHub: Basic Shell Script&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version control has become an essential tool for keeping track when working on data projects, as well as collaborating. RStudio supports working with Git, an open source distributed version control system, which is easy to use when combined with GitHub, a web-based Git repository hosting service. In this unit you will expand your data working environment, install Git and connect to GitHub through RStudio. You will learn how to use git to track changes to your work over time, and how to “branch” your project into a separate copy that can be developed further in isolation from the main code or merged back into the main trunk. You will discover why GitHub is useful for reproducible analysis and collaboration with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explain the difference between Git and GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To communicate with others on GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create a new and clone an existing repository on GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use the shell commands to do basic version control with Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To fork, branch and collaborate using GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good habits and practice of integrating Git and GitHub into your R project workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-4&#34;&gt;Unit 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic Statistical Concepts: Data classification, summary statistics and DA Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as you become more comfortable with the RStudio working environment, you will move on to mastering the key features of R language through the introduction of the fundamental statistical concepts. In this module you will learn the fundamental concepts of statistical modelling, starting with exploring the data by using appropriate plots and computation of descriptive statistics, and moving on to inferential statistics of parameter estimation and hypothesis testing. You will learn the process of generating conclusions about a population from a noisy sample. Using statistical inference through the navigation of the set of assumptions and tools, you will learn how to draw conclusions from data to generate new knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The concept of statistical distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to explore and visualise different data types using &lt;code&gt;base&lt;/code&gt; R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to adopt common data-analysis methodology when exploring relationships within data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The basics of inferential statistics by making valid generalizations from sample data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic tools for making statistical inference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduct explorative data analysis, interpret and report its outcomes in an appropriate manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-5&#34;&gt;Unit 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Wrangling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit you will learn some of the fundamental techniques for data exploration and transformation through the use of the &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; package. This &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; package helps make your exploration intuitive to write and easy to read. You will learn &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;’s key verbs for data manipulation that will help you uncover and shape the information within the data that is easy to turn into informative plots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;’s key data manipulation verbs: select, mutate, filter, arrange and summarise/summarize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To aggregate data by groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To chain data manipulation operations using the pipe operator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create summary statistics for a dataset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-6&#34;&gt;Unit 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Visualisation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit you will be introduced to the fundamental principles behind effective data visualisation. Through the use of the grammar of graphics plotting concepts implemented in the &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; package, you will be able to create meaningful exploratory plots. You will develop understanding about the way in which you should be able to think about necessary data transformations and summaries that can lead to an informative visualisation. You will learn how to create static maps and interactive maps with geolocated data by using the most popular packages in the R GIS community: simple features (&lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;code&gt;leaflet&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic principles of effective data visualisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To specify &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; building blocks and combine them to create a graphical display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About the philosophy that guides &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;: grammatical elements (layers) and aesthetic mapping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To visualise data with maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-7&#34;&gt;Unit 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducible Reporting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unit will give you an appreciation of R programming as a tool for reproducible reporting.  Adopting and applying open and transparent approaches to your DS project is integral to genuinely rigorous analysis and adds to the material value of one’s work. In view of this, the presentation of the available code, data and algorithms should be available to scrutiny and possible connectivity to the wider DS community. R Markdown and &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; make it easy to intermingle code and text to generate compelling reports and presentations that are never out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store in one place your data analysis methods, results and interpretation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update your data analysis methodology and automate the update of the results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write your DS report text and code in R Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate reproducible DS reports that display your code and results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assemble your DS reporting as either HTML, a PDF or a Word document using the package &lt;code&gt;rmarkdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-8&#34;&gt;Unit 8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unit provides much needed hands-on experience. You will work on a
on a real-life data problem that involves a complete data analysis, from data import to communication of results, with emphasis on reproducibility and transparency. You will develop you project openly on GitHub and make contributions to your fellow student whom you will communicate via GitHub Issues and who will review it and accepted it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To integrate different aspects of DS knowledge and skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To collaborate with others when working on a DS project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To gain exposure to an open source development process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To build personal DS portfolios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pulsar Mentoring Programme</title>
      <link>/programmes/programmes/mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/programmes/programmes/mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will be launching the first round of &lt;strong&gt;the Pulsar Mentoring Programme&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;31 October 2022&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to help more women and gender minority groups flourish in their careers through our mentoring programme, this will inspire and assist them to advance their careers through the application of DS and AI in their professional lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pulsar mentoring is a nine-month programme aimed at women and gender minority groups with a desire to enter the rapidly expanding world of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• We pair mentors and mentees across data driven industries and professions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Our candidates get the free access to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quantargo.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quantargo&lt;/a&gt; interactive online data science courses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This initiative feeds into Sister Analyst’s wider objectives to empower women and gender minority groups through the practice and application of DS and AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-pulsar&#34;&gt;Why Pulsar?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data, the LifeBlood of our new global life system, is a key resource in addressing the big global challenges of today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, more than ever, data literacy should be treated as a crucial skill for pretty much everyone. This is why we have partnered with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quantargo.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quantargo&lt;/a&gt; for the Pulsar Mentoring Programme to offer our candidates free access to interactive online data science courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The programme is inclusive and is designed for people at all walks of life and stages of their careers, regardless of technical acumen, to become more data-skilled. By empowering people to become more data capable we can deliver greater innovation, transparency, stability in market behaviour and improved social outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View &lt;a href=&#34;https://bit.ly/sapulsar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the Pulsar mentoring guide&lt;/a&gt; for more details on what the programme entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-can-i-get-involved&#34;&gt;How can I get involved?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in joining the network or signing up as a mentor or mentee, please fill the appropriate form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/8MPW8Qq6mjoyw3C7A&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;become a Pulsar’s mentee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/LiaQ8KzAV8jwjmVG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;become a Pulsar’s mentor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/programmes/mentoring_files/Screen Shot 2022-08-09 at 15.53.24.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or alternatively, get in touch and contact Sister Analyst at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:pulsar@sisteranalyst.org&#34;&gt;pulsar@sisteranalyst.org&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NextGen AI Festival</title>
      <link>/programmes/programmes/nextgen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/programmes/programmes/nextgen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The NextGen AI Festival&lt;/strong&gt; serves to increase diversity and inclusion in Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lives are becoming more aided and accommodated by a combination of science and many different technologies working together to enable computers to act and learn with human-like levels of intelligence. BooM! The world is changing in front of our eyes. Today&amp;rsquo;s innovations and prodigious levels of technology enablers have contributed to artificial intelligence (AI) becoming a more mainstream activity. AI aided tools are becoming more accessible and we are all becoming more enthralled by it. The Covid-19 pandemic has drawn everyone’s attention to how science and AI, when put together, make the impossible possible. We have all witnessed how AI and genomics reduce the time scales for scientific discovery and make precision medicine a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a surge of AI integration into user facing technology, public understanding of these technologies is still often rudimentary. The actuality is that consumers are adopting AI technology without understanding the real impact it could be having on their lives. At the same time, AI is being implemented by teams and organisations who still do not fully comprehend its potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To offset some of the potentially negative impacts of AI on society many discussions about ‘ethics’ are taking centre stage. But as the focus on AI bias and ethics grows, the scope of inquiry should clearly expand to consider not only how AI tools can be biased technically, but how they are shaped by the environments in which they are built and the people who build them. By integrating these concerns, we can develop a more accurate understanding of how AI can be developed and employed in ways that are fair and just, and how we might be able to ensure both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-do-we-need-it&#34;&gt;Why do we need it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a clear need for a better understanding of these developments from the perspectives of both learners, i.e. users and designers. In particular, we need to learn what the Next Generation wants from the world. The voices of the NextGen are what will create and form our future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Next Generation needs to become AI literate to fully comprehend the ways in which AI transforms the way that we communicate, work, and live with each other and with machines. With this in mind the NextGen AI Festival aims to connect today’s tech businesses that are implementing AI and the NextGen of AI users and future developers to help better understand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what competencies users need in order to effectively interact with and critically evaluate AI and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to design learner-centred AI technologies that foster increased user understanding of AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-aim&#34;&gt;Our Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;NextGen AI Festival&lt;/strong&gt; aims to democratise AI and create opportunities for underrepresented young talent through a combination of &lt;strong&gt;workshops&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;mentoring&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;hackathons&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;networking opportunities&lt;/strong&gt; to give young people &lt;strong&gt;aged 15-19&lt;/strong&gt; early exposure to &lt;strong&gt;AI for social  good and positive impact&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;NextGen AI Festival&lt;/strong&gt; is designed to serve ambitious high-school students who are open to learning. We will run workshops that will introduce the students to the technologies behind AI such as machine learning, deep learning, neural networks, and algorithms. The hackathons will provide workout spaces for searching and further expanding acquired &lt;strong&gt;AI skills and knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;. Mentored by practitioners from partnering companies and organisations and working in a team, each student will be able to implement the knowledge and ideas they have gained to provide AI driven solutions to &lt;strong&gt;real-world challenges&lt;/strong&gt;. The successful solutions will be showcased and the winning teams will be provided with an opportunity to use their skills in &lt;strong&gt;a real-world working environment&lt;/strong&gt;. They will be offered &lt;strong&gt;work experience summer break placements&lt;/strong&gt; provided by our partnering companies and organisations. This will provide a valuable experience of different aspects and insights into what it takes to run a successful data driven business.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feature and link using &lt;code&gt;slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload&lt;/strong&gt; an existing slide deck to &lt;code&gt;static/&lt;/code&gt; and link using &lt;code&gt;url_slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed&lt;/strong&gt; your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further event details, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;page elements&lt;/a&gt; such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women in Data Science Belgrade 2022</title>
      <link>/post/wids/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/wids/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first &lt;a href=&#34;https://widsbg2022.netlify.app&#34;&gt;WiDS Belgrade 2022&lt;/a&gt; conference, our 4th WiDS Serbia event, was a big success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 26th March, in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.icthub.rs&#34;&gt;ICT Hub&lt;/a&gt; Belgrade, a Women in Data Science (WiDS) Belgrade 2022 was hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/isidora-gataric/&#34;&gt;Isidora Gatarić&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/valentina-đorđević/&#34;&gt;Valentina Đorđević&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/tatjana-kecojevic-803704143/&#34;&gt;Tatjana Kecojevic&lt;/a&gt;, three WiDS Ambassadors based in Serbia. The conference is global initiative driven by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.widsconference.org&#34;&gt;Women in Data Science (WiDS)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stanford.edu&#34;&gt;Stanford University (USA)&lt;/a&gt;, and this year it was held at 200+ locations around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://widsbg2022.netlify.app&#34;&gt;WiDS Belgrade 2022&lt;/a&gt; event included two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: lower-roman&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robotics for mums and kids organised by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/anica-pavlovi%C4%87-91299341/&#34;&gt;Anica (Vulović) Pavlović&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://dic.rs&#34;&gt;“Deciji Inovativni Centar”&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DS panel discussion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robotics technology influences every aspect of work and home. Robotics has the potential to positively transform lives and work practices. With this in mind the next generation of its users needs to learn and recognise the application of STEAM as a multi and cross disciplinary concept is an empowering undertaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/robotics2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraging a passion for Maths and Science is a starting point as is elevating the many achievements of women involved in Data Science and data driven industries in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/robotics1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We at Sister Analyst believe that establishing supportive communities with a cross section of data literacy skills is a necessary step in the direction of empowering women in the workplace. Guided by this conviction, we organised four discussion panels within which we covered a wide spectrum of related DS subjects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HR, Employment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analytics and engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/wids1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four excellent panel discussions covered a wide spectrum of related DS subjects and the panellists share their personal professional experiences of working within data driven environments. Additionally, they discussed wider issues concerning entrepreneurship and education. Accordingly, on 4 panel dicussions of 4 different topics, we had 19 fantastic guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions began with the Business Development and Data Science panel, were
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/branislava-subotin-7750b8137/&#34;&gt;Branislava Subotin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ljubica-vujovic-2375a885/&#34;&gt;Ljubica Vujović&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/anita-jovic/&#34;&gt;Anita Jović&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/danijela-cabarkapa-99691716/&#34;&gt;Danijela Čabarkapa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jelena-roksandi%C4%87/&#34;&gt;Jelena Roksandić&lt;/a&gt; discussed how they handle their business topics in Data Science oriented teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/p1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educational themes were highlighted and discussed at the second panel. There &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jelenajovanovic.net/&#34;&gt;Jelena Jovanović&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/donandjela/&#34;&gt;Anđela Donević&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://rgf.bg.ac.rs/page.php?page=profesori_details&amp;amp;id=219&#34;&gt;Ranka Stanković&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirjana-katic-48b215233/&#34;&gt;Mirjana Katić&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/katarina-andjelkovic-02952616/&#34;&gt;Katarina Anđelković&lt;/a&gt; discussed in detail the formal and informal education situation relating to Data Science in Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/p2.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the third panel, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sonjacetkovic/&#34;&gt;Sonja Ćetković&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/bucalina/&#34;&gt;Ivana Bučalina&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vanja-vlaski/&#34;&gt;Vanja Vlaški&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ana-toskic-81349619/&#34;&gt;Ana Toskić&lt;/a&gt; dicussed employment and job/intern oportunities in the Data Science market in Serbia. Subjects such as recruitment processes and data privacy in Serbia were debated and considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/p3.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our final panel was dedicated to technical subjects related to Data Science jobs, such as data analytics, data science and engineering tasks and this discussion was conducted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ana-dukic-55061616a/&#34;&gt;Ana Dukić&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/marija-gavrilovic-67280995/&#34;&gt;Marija Gavrilović&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/tamara-krivokuca/&#34;&gt;Tamara Krivokuća&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/milena-k-57947430/&#34;&gt;Milena Kojić&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/tijana-dragojevi%C4%87-9715a6152/&#34;&gt;Tijana Dragojević&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/p4.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was well attended, a fantastic first here in Belgrade and we enjoyed adopting a new format for our event. Robotics for mum and kids was a fun way to engage with children in their process of learning important STEAM related skills. Highlighting the potential for the application of STEAM as a multi and cross disciplinary concept is an empowering undertaking. Just as smart technology offer connectivity far beyond our imagination, robots are beginning to exceed physical capabilities using artificial intelligence (AI), and cognitive skills far beyond our expectations. It can help solve significant challenges such as current environmental threats and global conflicts. It is important to prepare next generation for the future, and most importantly, have fun learning and experimenting with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/robotics3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panel discussions were a useful way to trigger an exchange of viewpoints among experts in response to very well thought questions from our fantastic moderator &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/isidora-gataric/&#34;&gt;Isidora&lt;/a&gt;. They involved on-the-spot interaction among the panellists with Isidora directing them from the beginning of each of the session to the end. All four panels sparked thought-provoking conversations between expert panellists, enabling the audience to learn from their discourse and interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WiDS Belgrade 2022&lt;/strong&gt; was an illustration of a simple way of the actions and activities that can be introduced to support our children to understand data driven technology for their future. Through the interactive panel discussions we meaningfully engaged with the participating actors and everyone with the desire to enter the rapidly expanding world of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During all of the sessions initiatives were discussed and new friendships formed and there is now a clear commitment to pushing ahead with our strategies for building on the foundations set at the conference. We are sure that we will meet up next year in an even greater number expanding our platform for networking and knowledge sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/wids0.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/anica-pavlovi%C4%87-91299341/&#34;&gt;Anica (Vulović) Pavlović&lt;/a&gt; and her &lt;a href=&#34;http://dic.rs&#34;&gt;“Deciji Inovativni Centar”&lt;/a&gt; for organising and hosting the robotics for kids and their mums workshop
&lt;img src=&#34;images/dic.png&#34; width=&#34;25%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.icthub.rs&#34;&gt;ICT Hub&lt;/a&gt; for sponsoring and hosting this event at their Belgrade Hub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/icthub.png&#34; width=&#34;15%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Women in STEM Network</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rcc.int&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Regional Cooperation Council (RCC)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.undp.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)&lt;/a&gt; assembled a group of women from Albania, Bosnia and Hercegovina, Kosovo*, Montenegro, North Macedonia and Serbia. The objective was to meet and work as a group as a means of establishing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rcc.int/events/1423/women-economic-empowerment-wee-launch-of-the-regional-network-of-women-in-stem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Regional Network of Women in STEM&lt;/a&gt; (Science, Technology, Engineering and Maths). The Women in STEM Network aims to expand opportunities for girls and women in educational and workplace contexts within the Western Balkans, focussing on STEM related fields. Ingrained patriarchal values and traditional culture norms are hindrances to women’s empowerment and gender equality in the Western Balkans (WB) region. This group of women are determined to address and resolve this and any other obstacles to the progress and empowerment of women in STEM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of COVID-19 resulted in a significant step backwards to recent progress regarding the reduction of gender segregation within occupations and women’s under-employment. The unequal participation in domestic duties has disproportionately impacted on the economic actualities of working women. At the same time, during the COVID-19 crisis, companies have accelerated their digital transformation as a crucial strategy for survival and future success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analytics and automation are absolutely key to successful digital transformation for
businesses of all sizes. The global pandemic, seismic in its impact, has both accelerated the need for robust transformation strategies and simultaneously highlighted the cracks and strains relating to gender employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the life-blood of our network is STEM education as an integrated, interdisciplinary approach to learning that provides hands-on learning experiences for students and wider communities. We see STEM teaching and learning beyond the mere transfer of knowledge. It is a mechanism for initiating and equipping learners with critical thinking, problem solving, creative and collaborative skills. This mechanism ultimately establishes interconnected relationships between work places, schools and communities and regional economies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the pandemic, organizations were struggling to recruit and retain people
with the skills needed to help them succeed in a data-driven world. Part of the
solution is to retrain current workforces into productive data analytic practitioners, which are closely STEM related. A person-centred approach is essential to success, as is infusing a culture of familiarity and expertise with data analytics overarching various organisations. Focussing on human-centred approaches makes data analytics accessible to a broader demographic, particularly women, which is now more than ever crucial in the current working environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the pandemic it has become even more obvious that in order to gain a competitive advantage in a business environment, companies will have to provide an inclusive framework supporting work life balance and flexible work arrangements. By doing this, they will attract and retain a talented workforce and enhance women’s access to non-traditional jobs. It is very desirable to introduce certification for gender equality standards, to encourage and recognise commitment to advancing the careers of women in STEM. Certification showcases a company’s commitment to gender equality and transparency and helps to create a cultural perception of a more equal and fairer society in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all recognise that in addition to addressing the talent pipeline issue and encouraging more young women to pursue careers in STEM related fields, there is more that industry can and should do. We have an obligation to be mutually supportive; this is the first step in countering unconscious bias and genuinely empowering people. Difference is an accelerator of innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is now agreed that the Women in STEM Network is going to be based on a data driven framework with the principles of equity, partnership, and sustainability. The network will seek smart, scalable solutions that lead to removing barriers and creating equitable access and opportunities for historically underserved groups of women. Gender focus is at the heart of the process of developing new programs and initiating projects as a means of closing the gender gap. Our initiative seeks to develop mechanisms of support for women as they strive to become leaders, critical thinkers, and creators. The networks created will develop new programs, projects, funding opportunities and consequently create greater opportunities for gender minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core team of the network incorporates a representative from each country. &lt;a href=&#34;https://tatjanakeco.rbind.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr
Tatjana Kecojevic&lt;/a&gt; is the lead representative for the Serbian National Women in STEM Network. Tatjana is a data scientist with a doctorate in Statistics from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.manchester.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;University of Manchester&lt;/a&gt;. She spent many years working in the U.K. university sector as a senior lecturer and has published an extensive number of articles and papers relating to data analysis. Tatjana established the chapters of &lt;a href=&#34;https://rladies.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R-Ladies&lt;/a&gt; Manchester, Belgrade and Novi Sad and is a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://forwards.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R Forwards&lt;/a&gt; team and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.widsconference.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Women in DS (WiDS)&lt;/a&gt; ambassador - roles dedicated to empowering women. Currently, she is the director of &lt;a href=&#34;https://sisteranalyst.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SisterAnalyst.org&lt;/a&gt;, an organisation aiming to empower women from a diverse range of backgrounds through data literacy. In addition to her involvement supporting women in STEM related activities, she is dedicated to creating an inclusive culture by developing community initiatives supporting all underrepresented groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sister Analyst believes that establishing supportive communities with a cross section of data literacy skills is a necessary step in the direction of empowering women in the workplace. We are convinced that you do not need to be a maths or computer person; it is all about learning to ask the right questions when in possession of available data. Our regional STEM Networks will bring educators, business leaders, STEM professionals, and community leaders together to build success connecting STEM career opportunities within their communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;* In the context of the UN Resolution 1244/1999&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Air pollution in Belgrade</title>
      <link>/post/oh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/oh/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier in March we ran our first ever &lt;a href=&#34;https://openheroines.org&#34;&gt;Open Heroines&lt;/a&gt; event here in Belgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got things started by creating &lt;a href=&#34;https://ohsa.netlify.app/&#34;&gt;a website&lt;/a&gt; publicising our event and making it clear from the get go what the participants could expect from the event. The website was created in &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;blogdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://themes.gohugo.io&#34;&gt;HUGO&lt;/a&gt; and deployed using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;. The responses to the site were very positive and we were particularly bowled over by the wide range of backgrounds of the people wishing to attend. From economists to journalists, students to CEOs, the desire to understand more about the power of data acted as the adhesive to the collective ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We illustrated the process of the democratisation of open data. In the belief that we should use a topical subject for analysis, we looked at data related to air pollution in Belgrade sourced from &lt;a href=&#34;https://klimerko.org&#34;&gt;Vazduh Gradjanima&lt;/a&gt; – a hot talking point within the city. We created R-Markdown reports where the participants created visual data reporting of the core issues related to air pollution. There was an amazing response to everyone being able to learn how to interact with data, as if a new world was now available to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of transparency and reproducibility for those who were not fortunate to join us in learning how to use R and analyse this air pollution data, we uploaded our findings to the GitHub &lt;a href=&#34;https://tanjakec.github.io/OH_workshop/OHSA.html&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://tanjakec.github.io/OH_workshop/OHSA.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example preprint / working paper</title>
      <link>/publication/preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>/slides/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/slides/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-slides-in-markdown-with-wowchemy&#34;&gt;Create slides in Markdown with Wowchemy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wowchemy&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://owchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiently write slides in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-in-1: Create, Present, and Publish your slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports speaker notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;code&gt;Right Arrow&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;code&gt;Left Arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start: &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview: &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaker notes: &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fullscreen: &lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom: &lt;code&gt;Alt + Click&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js#pdf-export&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF Export&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-highlighting&#34;&gt;Code Highlighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inline code: &lt;code&gt;variable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;porridge = &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;
if porridge == &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;:
    print(&amp;quot;Eating...&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In-line math: $x + y = z$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
f\left( x \right) = ;\frac{{2\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x - 4} \right)}}{{\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x + 1} \right)}}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragments&#34;&gt;Fragments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make content appear incrementally&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{% fragment %}} One {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} **Two** {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} Three {{% /fragment %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to play!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
One
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
Three
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fragment can accept two optional parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;: use a custom style (requires definition in custom CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weight&lt;/code&gt;: sets the order in which a fragment appears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaker-notes&#34;&gt;Speaker Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add speaker notes to your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% speaker_note %}}
- Only the speaker can read these notes
- Press `S` key to view
{{% /speaker_note %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press the &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view the speaker notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the speaker can read these notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black: Black background, white text, blue links (default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;league: Gray background, white text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beige: Beige background, dark text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sky: Blue background, thin dark text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;night: Black background, thick white text, orange links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serif: Cappuccino background, gray text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solarized: Cream-colored background, dark green text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;section data-noprocess data-shortcode-slide
  
      
      data-background-image=&#34;/media/boards.jpg&#34;
  &gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-slide&#34;&gt;Custom Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customize the slide style and background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; slide background-image=&amp;quot;/media/boards.jpg&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide background-color=&amp;quot;#0000FF&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide class=&amp;quot;my-style&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-css-example&#34;&gt;Custom CSS Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make headers navy colored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;assets/css/reveal_custom.css&lt;/code&gt; with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;.reveal section h1,
.reveal section h2,
.reveal section h3 {
  color: navy;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wowchemy/wowchemy-hugo-modules/discussions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Project</title>
      <link>/project/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>External Project</title>
      <link>/project/external-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/external-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internal Project</title>
      <link>/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example journal article</title>
      <link>/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example conference paper</title>
      <link>/publication/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example conference paper</title>
      <link>/publication/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
