<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fundamental DS and AI skills | SisterAnalyst</title>
    <link>/courses/programmes/</link>
      <atom:link href="/courses/programmes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Fundamental DS and AI skills</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/SA_hex.png</url>
      <title>Fundamental DS and AI skills</title>
      <link>/courses/programmes/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>/courses/programmes/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/programmes/overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;fundamental-ds-and-ai-skills-data-skills-for-work&#34;&gt;Fundamental DS and AI skills: data skills for work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Science (DS) and Artificial Intelligence (AI) are an essential part of a data-driven culture. The aim of this course is to provide a solid foundation for understanding data, in particular how to read, work with, analyse and communicate with data. They are skills that empower people from all walks of life at all levels of work. It is a set of skills that is also likely to improve digital literacy. As data is so crucial for organisational success, data literacy and associated meta-skills are intrinsically in demand for all employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By applying AI algorithms, we draw answers from data, which is why fundamental coding and data skills are necessary for developing strong conceptual understanding of the technologies behind AI. Our course will develop your confidence and skills to drive and sustain data driven innovation whether you study, work or you acquire them for your everyday life. The course focuses on teaching individuals the practical and technical skills needed to analyse and solve intricate data problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the course, you will be introduced to a wide variety of free and open source tools commonly used when working on a data project. You will apply these tools in many practical activities and case studies, solving problems that involve finding and evaluating information, performing calculations and data wrangling that will enable you to draw reasoned conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will start from zero, with no prior knowledge required, and work our way up to advanced data analysis using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, a public domain language for data analysis. The curriculum covers the relevant tools and technologies including Fundamental Coding and Basic Statistical Concepts through the use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. R amalgamates the learning of important and desirable data skills: code writing for statistical modelling, and visualisation and data reporting in a reproducible manner. You will learn how to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;, a version control system, to track changes when working on a data project in a transparent and reproducible manner that fosters knowledge sharing and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be guided by skilled instructors and will gain real-world experience by collaborating with your peers on real-life data projects provided by our partner companies and organisations. You will build a comprehensive portfolio throughout the learning experience, giving you the confidence needed to tap into related industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our local and international partners will provide a unique opportunity for you to work on real-life projects that will help grow your skills, build your profile, and create a platform for your data literacy empowered career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the course you will have the solid understanding needed to be able to further grow your data knowledge skills once the course is complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;course-objectives&#34;&gt;Course Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn fundamental concepts of computer coding along with problem solving techniques and analytical thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to analyse problem requirements to recognise what type of data and processes are involved in the solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to navigate the entire data science pipeline from data acquisition to publication: access, explore, visualise, and analyse data in a reproducible and shareable manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on case studies inspired by real problems and based on real-world data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become aware of, and recognise the huge potential for data science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-course-works-teaching-and-learning-strategy&#34;&gt;How the course works: Teaching and Learning Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material is structured within a series of eight weekly specialised units that will help you master the skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each unit is split into two hands-on taught lessons that will be delivered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wednesdays, between 18:00 - 21:00 as an on-line session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturdays, between 10:00 - 14:00 as an on-site session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and it will require a minimum of 3 hours guided independent study time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each unit will be taught by our instructors and will cover various related topics through appropriate case studies, presentations, readings and discussion forums. The conceptual ideas come to life when practice becomes reality which is why the material is designed as hands-on taught lessons, through the application of R. The course provides the opportunity for participants to test their knowledge, both conceptual and practical by adopting an interactive student/teacher approach. Students are expected to use their own time to practise and hone the data handling expertise acquired during the sessions.
To provide a structure in learning to communicate newly acquired concepts you will be paired with a fellow student. You will practise explaining new concepts and skills to one another, which will advance your learning and develop the essential collaboration skills you will need in a data driven work place environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students are expected to participate fully in all of these delivery modes, but in particular are expected to have attempted any pre-set work, and come fully prepared to discuss any problems encountered and debate the ideas and any issues raised. We recommend you complete each of the following before the end of each week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readings and hand-outs/exercises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participation in the discussion forums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quizzes covering concepts from tutorials and/or readings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To earn your certificate, you will need to successfully complete the final project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Course material will be delivered in English and Serbian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-can-enrol&#34;&gt;Who can enrol&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is for people from varying backgrounds and diverse profiles with very little or no coding or data analytic experience. The course will benefit anyone who has the curiosity and desire to enter the realm of data science. We will make sense of the world of data and learn effective and attractive ways to visually analyse and communicate related information. With the knowledge gained on this course, you will be ready to undertake your very own data analysis for the first time.
Data Science is not simply fashionable jargon, but rather a set of tools that empower data enriched
living, so whatever industry you are in, this is relevant to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-is-eligible-for-our-course&#34;&gt;Who is eligible for our course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women and gender minorities over 18 years of age with priority given to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single Parents on low income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long-term unemployed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone experiencing problems getting the education needed to find meaningful work, through discrimination or otherwise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-can-apply-for-our-course&#34;&gt;Who can apply for our course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who recognise the paramount importance of data and its use and are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Able to commit to the course for its duration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Able to commit to all required sessions and the time requirements specified&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willing to share knowledge and return as a mentor or coach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The course is delivered twice a year.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our next available cohort starts on 02 March 2022.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indicative Syllabus</title>
      <link>/courses/programmes/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/programmes/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Learning units build on previous units and they should be learnt in the order presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-1&#34;&gt;Unit 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core DS/AI Concepts and Tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unit will cover the baseline knowledge you need before getting into the advanced coding aspects of DS/AI. We will discuss concepts and terminology related to data and data solutions. You will learn the fundamentals of computer science with “drag &amp;amp; drop blocks”. In order to become acquainted with the basic computational concepts of problem-solving, logical thinking, cause and effect within the context of modelling, you will be introduced to prime programming operations, control structures, data types, etc. We will finish by configuring your working environment and installing the software necessary when working on your future data projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To describe forms, formats, and lifecycles of data and how these vary across disciplines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To represent programming logic in pseudocode and/or flowcharts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic concepts such as data type and index&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use Boolean expressions in if-then structures for making decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use looping structures and how to end loops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create your own customised functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To install and run R/RStudio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-2&#34;&gt;Unit 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R in RStudio: syntax and working environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this module you will set up the working environment and pass the first big hurdle of importing data; you will learn how to do it the proper way with a command in R. You will learn how to use RStudio IDE for R from RStudio customisation to files navigation. You will learn good habits and practice of workflow in an R project. Once you get comfortable with the RStudio working environment, you will move on to mastering the key features of R language and its syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic use of R/RStudio console&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good habits for workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data structures, variables, and basic data collection techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inputting and importing different data types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R environment: record keeping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-3&#34;&gt;Unit 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Git in GitHub: Basic Shell Script&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version control has become an essential tool for keeping track when working on data projects, as well as collaborating. RStudio supports working with Git, an open source distributed version control system, which is easy to use when combined with GitHub, a web-based Git repository hosting service. In this unit you will expand your data working environment, install Git and connect to GitHub through RStudio. You will learn how to use git to track changes to your work over time, and how to “branch” your project into a separate copy that can be developed further in isolation from the main code or merged back into the main trunk. You will discover why GitHub is useful for reproducible analysis and collaboration with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explain the difference between Git and GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To communicate with others on GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create a new and clone an existing repository on GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use the shell commands to do basic version control with Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To fork, branch and collaborate using GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good habits and practice of integrating Git and GitHub into your R project workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-4&#34;&gt;Unit 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic Statistical Concepts: Data classification, summary statistics and DA Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as you become more comfortable with the RStudio working environment, you will move on to mastering the key features of R language through the introduction of the fundamental statistical concepts. In this module you will learn the fundamental concepts of statistical modelling, starting with exploring the data by using appropriate plots and computation of descriptive statistics, and moving on to inferential statistics of parameter estimation and hypothesis testing. You will learn the process of generating conclusions about a population from a noisy sample. Using statistical inference through the navigation of the set of assumptions and tools, you will learn how to draw conclusions from data to generate new knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The concept of statistical distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to explore and visualise different data types using &lt;code&gt;base&lt;/code&gt; R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to adopt common data-analysis methodology when exploring relationships within data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The basics of inferential statistics by making valid generalizations from sample data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic tools for making statistical inference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduct explorative data analysis, interpret and report its outcomes in an appropriate manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-5&#34;&gt;Unit 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Wrangling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit you will learn some of the fundamental techniques for data exploration and transformation through the use of the &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; package. This &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; package helps make your exploration intuitive to write and easy to read. You will learn &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;’s key verbs for data manipulation that will help you uncover and shape the information within the data that is easy to turn into informative plots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;’s key data manipulation verbs: select, mutate, filter, arrange and summarise/summarize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To aggregate data by groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To chain data manipulation operations using the pipe operator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create summary statistics for a dataset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-6&#34;&gt;Unit 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Visualisation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit you will be introduced to the fundamental principles behind effective data visualisation. Through the use of the grammar of graphics plotting concepts implemented in the &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; package, you will be able to create meaningful exploratory plots. You will develop understanding about the way in which you should be able to think about necessary data transformations and summaries that can lead to an informative visualisation. You will learn how to create static maps and interactive maps with geolocated data by using the most popular packages in the R GIS community: simple features (&lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;code&gt;leaflet&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic principles of effective data visualisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To specify &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; building blocks and combine them to create a graphical display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About the philosophy that guides &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;: grammatical elements (layers) and aesthetic mapping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To visualise data with maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-7&#34;&gt;Unit 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducible Reporting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unit will give you an appreciation of R programming as a tool for reproducible reporting.  Adopting and applying open and transparent approaches to your DS project is integral to genuinely rigorous analysis and adds to the material value of one’s work. In view of this, the presentation of the available code, data and algorithms should be available to scrutiny and possible connectivity to the wider DS community. R Markdown and &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; make it easy to intermingle code and text to generate compelling reports and presentations that are never out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store in one place your data analysis methods, results and interpretation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update your data analysis methodology and automate the update of the results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write your DS report text and code in R Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate reproducible DS reports that display your code and results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assemble your DS reporting as either HTML, a PDF or a Word document using the package &lt;code&gt;rmarkdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-8&#34;&gt;Unit 8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unit provides much needed hands-on experience. You will work on a
on a real-life data problem that involves a complete data analysis, from data import to communication of results, with emphasis on reproducibility and transparency. You will develop you project openly on GitHub and make contributions to your fellow student whom you will communicate via GitHub Issues and who will review it and accepted it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will learn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To integrate different aspects of DS knowledge and skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To collaborate with others when working on a DS project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To gain exposure to an open source development process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To build personal DS portfolios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pulsar Mentoring Programme</title>
      <link>/courses/programmes/mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/programmes/mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Pulsar mentoring programme is aimed at women and gender minority groups with a desire to enter the rapidly expanding world of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of the mentoring programme is to accelerate the personal and professional development of our candidates, inspiring and assisting them to realise their potential through the application of DS and AI in their professional lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the help of our mentors we are breaking gender barriers and navigating the skills essential for discovering future data empowered careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking practical steps we keep them moving in the direction of becoming data empowered professionals. Based on the candidates’ experiences we assign mentors who will guide and support them to develop the necessary skills and to gain practical project experience. Together they will create a friendly, safe, and confidential environment for communication and informal discussions. The programme lasts six months and goes through four key stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Getting to know one another and explore areas where the mentee may need support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Moving forward in helping the mentee identify their needs and finding the ways in which the mentor can help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 3&lt;/strong&gt;: Developing a mentoring strategy for achieving the set goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 4&lt;/strong&gt;: Reviewing the progression of the mentoring plan and reflecting on what has been achieved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this mentoring programme, we will expose many candidates to data related practices and help them to nurture their interest in applying these practices to their everyday work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mentoring programme aims to be inclusive; we are the antithesis of exclusivity, we believe in active engagement, knowledge acquisition and building skills for future goals and milestones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;guide&#34;&gt;Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mentoring Programme plan will serve as a framework and roadmap to identify its priorities and to designate roles, responsibilities, and criteria for meeting those priorities. The programme plan will provide a systematic process to carry out the mission of providing lifelong, blended learning and developmental opportunities for our candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;broad-roles-and-responsibilities&#34;&gt;Broad roles and responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good working relationship requires respect, self-awareness, inclusion, open communication and trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mentor&#34;&gt;Mentor&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mentor motivates their mentees to do their best work and take steps that will help career advancement using data skills. Through discussions a mentor identifies needs, assimilates the mentee into the wider data driven community, and assists them in developing short- and long-term goals.
Thanks to being able to give back to the community the mentor benefits from this relationship in the form of personal satisfaction. It enables the mentor to build a legacy of knowledge, gain new insight and experience whilst enhancing visibility and prestige.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mentor shall provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insight, constructive feedback and encouragement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A safe environment for taking actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agreed-upon commitment of time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mentee&#34;&gt;Mentee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mentee should be committed to professional growth and should be driven to succeed. A mentee should acknowledge the time and effort that the mentor puts into providing support and establishing a relationship. They can do this by showing a willingness to take the initiative in asking relevant questions, responding to the provided feedback and by seeking new learning opportunities.
A mentee benefits from this relationship by acquiring personal education and by gaining exposureand opportunities for advancement within the DS and AI community. In this way a mentee constructs a greater awareness of career and personal capabilities and possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mentee should be willing to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess his or her individual needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the initiative in skill and career development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participate in the mentoring relationship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop and utilize the skills of professionalism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;establishing-the-relationship&#34;&gt;Establishing the Relationship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both sides, the mentor and mentee, should consider their intentions and expectations for the relationship before they even meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mentor-first-meeting&#34;&gt;Mentor: first meeting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prepare for the first meeting, a mentor should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summarize goals and expectations for the mentoring partnership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List two to three topics to discuss with the mentee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the logistics of monthly meetings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the questions a mentor can prepare for the first meeting might include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you tell me about your background and experience when working with data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What gives you the most satisfaction? Frustration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you like to spend your free time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who do you admire the most or find the most interesting? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you use your data skills on the job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which relevant data skills do you want to develop? How can I help?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What attracted you to this programme?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often would you like to connect?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six months from now, how would you like to have grown as a result of this mentoring relationship?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What one thing can I do to ensure a positive experience for you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should I expect from you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mentee-first-meeting&#34;&gt;Mentee: first meeting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prepare for the first meeting, a mentee should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider goals and expectations for the mentoring partnership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the logistics and frequency of meetings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare talking points for introductory phone calls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the questions a mentee can prepare for the first meeting might include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you had past successes in mentoring individuals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m seeking specific “xyz” skills for my professional development. Can you help me attain them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What expectations do you generally have of the people you mentor?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time can you offer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can I plan for our next meeting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first informational interview/meeting should result in the following outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A decision&lt;/strong&gt;. Do you want to enter into a mentoring partnership with this person?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An answer&lt;/strong&gt;. Does this person have the knowledge to help you define your goals and turn them into reality?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;follow-up-meetings&#34;&gt;Follow up meetings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the match has been made it is important that both the mentor and mentee take ownership of their participation in the programme and agree on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;where and when the subsequent meetings will take place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;regularity of meetings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;methods of contact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what would be achievable goals and objectives within the time scale of the programme, i.e. what happens next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;best practice in working towards the agreed aims and objectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mentor and mentee will determine the final mix of activities for the programme, but they should include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;goal-setting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;documentation review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;evaluation and closure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By its very nature, mentoring is rewarding and valuable for both sides involved. The sharing of knowledge, expertise and insight helps to create more motivated and accomplished professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recognition-and-reward&#34;&gt;Recognition and reward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To acknowledge the work and effort required from all parties involved in this programme two events are planned. The events will serve to promote and publicise the success of the programme by encouraging both mentors and mentees to talk about their experience and showcase their achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources-used&#34;&gt;Resources used&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide is adapted from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share. Learn. Grow. Mentor. A How-to Guide&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aicpa.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AICPA&lt;/a&gt; Women’s Initiatives Executive Committee. Available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aicpa.org/Career/WomenintheProfession/DownloadableDocuments/mentor.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.aicpa.org/Career/WomenintheProfession/DownloadableDocuments/mentor.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mentoring Programme Guidance: Step-by-Step Guide&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.architecture.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RIBA Architecture&lt;/a&gt;. Available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.architecture.com/-/media/gathercontent/mentoring-guidance/additional-documents/mentoringprogrammeguidanceastepbystepguidepdf.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.architecture.com/-/media/gathercontent/mentoring-guidance/additional-documents/mentoringprogrammeguidanceastepbystepguidepdf.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NextGen AI Festival</title>
      <link>/courses/programmes/nextgen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/programmes/nextgen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The NextGen AI Festival&lt;/strong&gt; serves to increase diversity and inclusion in Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lives are becoming more aided and accommodated by a combination of science and many different technologies working together to enable computers to act and learn with human-like levels of intelligence. BooM! The world is changing in front of our eyes. Today&amp;rsquo;s innovations and prodigious levels of technology enablers have contributed to artificial intelligence (AI) becoming a more mainstream activity. AI aided tools are becoming more accessible and we are all becoming more enthralled by it. The Covid-19 pandemic has drawn everyone’s attention to how science and AI, when put together, make the impossible possible. We have all witnessed how AI and genomics reduce the time scales for scientific discovery and make precision medicine a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a surge of AI integration into user facing technology, public understanding of these technologies is still often rudimentary. The actuality is that consumers are adopting AI technology without understanding the real impact it could be having on their lives. At the same time, AI is being implemented by teams and organisations who still do not fully comprehend its potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To offset some of the potentially negative impacts of AI on society many discussions about ‘ethics’ are taking centre stage. But as the focus on AI bias and ethics grows, the scope of inquiry should clearly expand to consider not only how AI tools can be biased technically, but how they are shaped by the environments in which they are built and the people who build them. By integrating these concerns, we can develop a more accurate understanding of how AI can be developed and employed in ways that are fair and just, and how we might be able to ensure both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-do-we-need-it&#34;&gt;Why do we need it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a clear need for a better understanding of these developments from the perspectives of both learners, i.e. users and designers. In particular, we need to learn what the Next Generation wants from the world. The voices of the NextGen are what will create and form our future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Next Generation needs to become AI literate to fully comprehend the ways in which AI transforms the way that we communicate, work, and live with each other and with machines. With this in mind the NextGen AI Festival aims to connect today’s tech businesses that are implementing AI and the NextGen of AI users and future developers to help better understand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what competencies users need in order to effectively interact with and critically evaluate AI and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to design learner-centred AI technologies that foster increased user understanding of AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-aim&#34;&gt;Our Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;NextGen AI Festival&lt;/strong&gt; aims to democratise AI and create opportunities for underrepresented young talent through a combination of &lt;strong&gt;workshops&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;mentoring&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;hackathons&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;networking opportunities&lt;/strong&gt; to give young people &lt;strong&gt;aged 15-19&lt;/strong&gt; early exposure to &lt;strong&gt;AI for social  good and positive impact&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;NextGen AI Festival&lt;/strong&gt; is designed to serve ambitious high-school students who are open to learning. We will run workshops that will introduce the students to the technologies behind AI such as machine learning, deep learning, neural networks, and algorithms. The hackathons will provide workout spaces for searching and further expanding acquired &lt;strong&gt;AI skills and knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;. Mentored by practitioners from partnering companies and organisations and working in a team, each student will be able to implement the knowledge and ideas they have gained to provide AI driven solutions to &lt;strong&gt;real-world challenges&lt;/strong&gt;. The successful solutions will be showcased and the winning teams will be provided with an opportunity to use their skills in &lt;strong&gt;a real-world working environment&lt;/strong&gt;. They will be offered &lt;strong&gt;work experience summer break placements&lt;/strong&gt; provided by our partnering companies and organisations. This will provide a valuable experience of different aspects and insights into what it takes to run a successful data driven business.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
